Speaker 1: the fundamentals are we have so much debt this whole economy is such a massive bubble that if we actually tried to do what paul volcker did we would create an economic condition much worse than what they perceive the threat to be from inflation so they're not going to do anything but at this point i think the fed is now damned that they do or we're damned if they do and we're damned if they don't because even if the fed doesn't hike rates the markets are going to crash if it does hike rates, they're going to crash even more.
Speaker 2: Earlier
Speaker 3: today, the Federal Reserve announced that it left its policy rate unchanged. That was widely
Speaker 4: expected, although there was about a 30% probability of a quarter point rate hike.
And
Speaker 4: even if we didn't get a quarter point rate hike, I think it would have been much too little, much too late to actually do anything to achieve the Fed's 2% inflation target. I think a lot more would be needed, not only a bigger rate hike.
But
Speaker 4: the Fed would have to do something about the size of its balance sheet and money supply growth. They would have to shrink the balance sheet and start shrinking money supply, the opposite of what is continuing to happen so far ever since Warsh took over as Fed chair. But anyway, it was not a unanimous vote. There were three FOMC members that did vote for a quarter point rate hike.
Speaker 4: But Kevin Walsh was not among them. He voted to leave interest rates unchanged. The rate is three and a half to three and three quarters. By the way, that's where the rate has been since December of last year, when the Fed cut rates by 25 basis points. But for the last or for five months
Speaker 5: before Walsh took over, rates were exactly where they are right
now.
And
Speaker 4: Warsh has been FOMC chairman
Speaker 1: now for what, a couple of months. This is his second press conference that he had today, the second opportunity that he's had to match up his rhetoric with actions. The markets thought there was a 30% chance of a rate hike. Why not deliver one? The
fact of the
Speaker 1: matter is, and I've been saying this from the beginning before,
Speaker 1: He's all bark and
Speaker 5: no bite. He can talk the talk, and he talked it again today, but he can't walk the walk. And the markets now are starting to take notice of what I have been talking
Speaker 4: about. Now, first of all, before he took the Q&A, he delivered his prepared remarks. And during those remarks,
Speaker 4: Number one, the first thing he did was praise the committee. Oh, how great the committee is. They've done an excellent job, right? Everybody is
Speaker 1: great on the FOMC. Talked about how great the economy is, how resilient the economy is.
And I
Speaker 1: think he does that because that's what Trump wants to pretend. So I think he wants to continue the pretense by reiterating how we've got this great economy so Trump can take credit for it. But then he...
Speaker 1: continued about how the Fed is resolute in its resolve to bring down inflation. It's resolute.
And he
Speaker 1: also said that given the fact that inflation has been above 2% for over five years, that the markets may believe that the Fed really has a
Speaker 1: inflation target above 2%. After all, if the inflation target really was 2%, then why would the Fed tolerate it being above 2% for so long? Maybe it's a soft 2. Maybe the Fed has a secret target that's north of 2, and it's just not letting the markets know. Well, what Warsh wanted to make sure is that that belief was extinguished.
Speaker 1: that it's not the case, certainly not under his watch, even if that may have been the case, and he didn't admit that it was, but he made it clear in his
Speaker 6: rhetoric that it's not the case now, that the Fed does not have a secret target higher than 2%. 2% is the target. Now, of course, it also means that if 2% was the target all along, if there was no secret higher target, then the Fed failed the Fed was not
Speaker 6: able to achieve 2% inflation despite the fact that that was its goal. And of course, the reason that the Fed never achieved 2% inflation was for precisely the reasons that I stated in the past. Monetary policy never got restrictive enough to reduce inflation to 2%. In fact, monetary policy remained accommodative despite all of the Fed's rate hikes.
Speaker 6: because the entire time the Fed was hiking rates under Powell, money supply growth only shrank briefly. Credit never contracted. The government, corporations, individuals continued to borrow more money. So you had more credit chasing a supply of goods. Remember, inflation is not just the expansion of the money supply.
but
Speaker 6: the expansion of credit because you don't need money to buy stuff. Just ask just about any American. You could have no money and keep on spending because you can spend credit as easily as you can spend money. And spending credit also pushes up prices. That's the demand. If the Fed wants to get inflation down, it has to bring down that demand, which means it has to raise rates enough to tighten credit.
Speaker 6: Consumers have to borrow less. The government has to borrow less. Businesses have to borrow less, but none of that happened. Everybody kept on borrowing and kept on spending. And that's why inflation didn't go back down to 2%. Now, it went down a little bit. You know, the taper, the rates came down from the peak, but that was just temporary. Now we're seeing a resurgence because the inflation fire never got put out. The Fed didn't want to.
Speaker 6: Because as soon as you got problems in the economy, as soon as you got banks that were failing, that's when the Fed stopped hiking. And I said this all along. The Fed surrendered. In fact, Powell always made a big deal about the fact that, hey, we got rid of inflation without causing a recession, without seeing a meaningful increase in unemployment. And they were bragging about that, like, hey, nobody thought we could do it. We pulled it off. Well, the reason that...
Speaker 6: They won the inflation war without that collateral damage is because they really didn't win. They surrendered before the damage became too great. And that's why inflation never went away, because the Fed didn't have what it takes to get rid of it. It chose inflation, which is something that Warsh gets right. He says inflation is a choice. Absolutely. His predecessors chose inflation.
Speaker 6: And it's obvious by his deeds, not by his words, but by his deeds that Warsh is making the exact same choice for the exact same reasons. That's why he didn't hike rates today. Why? Because had the Fed hiked rates, the markets would have tanked. Now they tanked anyway. They just would have tanked even more had they raised rates.
And I
Speaker 6: think that's why he didn't do it. But again,
Speaker 6: He can't admit that. And I pointed this out, even before I get into the Q&A today, I pointed this out based on the testimony from a week or two ago when Worf testified before the House and the
Senate, and
Speaker 6: in particular, the Senate, when Senator Kennedy asked him specifically, what are you going to do to reduce inflation?
Speaker 6: And he had three things that he was going to do. And all three amounted to talking tough on inflation and letting everybody know how committed he was, how resolute they were, how much they owned the inflation problem, and that they were determined, unlike predecessors maybe, to solve the problem. That is exactly what he did
with an
Speaker 6: opportunity to hike rates. He didn't do it.
Speaker 6: with an opportunity to go back to quantitative tightening. Didn't do that either. All he did is talk about how tough they were going to be, how they were serious about bringing down inflation, just like he said he was going to do. But he didn't do anything about it. If the Fed really is different, if it's really different now with the new sheriff in town,
Why
Speaker 6: are interest rates exactly the same as they were when he came to town? Rates are where they were during the five months before he became a Fed chair. And if he's basically saying, look, now we're really getting serious here. I'm resolved. We're going to bring inflation down to 2% because maybe in the past the Fed wasn't doing enough. Well, why haven't you? Why have you done nothing?
I
Speaker 6: mean, the only thing that he's done is they don't have forward guidance anymore.
But other
Speaker 6: than that, there is no change. It's exactly the same. And so clearly, Warsh is no more serious about bringing inflation down to 2% than was Powell.
And
Speaker 6: in fact, he voted with Powell, right? Powell was one of the other FOMC members that voted to keep rates unchanged. So he's basically voting exactly with his predecessor. Now, it's possible that
he
Speaker 4: actually wants to hike rates, but he didn't want to vote with the minority and have four votes. I don't think there's ever been a time that I can remember, or probably ever, where
Speaker 4: The FOMC went against the chair where the chair cast a minority vote. So maybe it's possible that knowing that he can only get three other people for a hike, he just decided to vote to stay pat because he was trying to spare the markets of of that problem, because
Speaker 1: that would have been a problem to see the Fed chair.
In
Speaker 1: the minority, meaning he had no control over the FOMC. So maybe he decided to go for no hike just because he knew that there was no way that they were going to get a hike. And, you know, they asked Donald Trump about the decision today. And, of course, had Powell still been Fed chair?
Speaker 1: He would have been all over this. He would have been calling Powell an idiot, a moron, you know, a low IQ person. How dare he? You know, we need to cut rates. He didn't do any of that. He basically just said, look, you know, Warsh is a very smart guy. He's a very competent guy. So he's doing what he's got to do.
Speaker 1: But then he said that, you know, he's got a very political board there. And so that makes it difficult for him to do the right thing. I'm sure he wants to cut rates. This is what Trump said. But, you know, he can't do it because he doesn't have the cooperation of this political FOMC. I think it's the opposite. I think he wants to raise rates. I mean, if he's serious...
Speaker 1: about wanting inflation at 2%, that he needs to raise rates. The reason he's not raising rates is because either he can't convince his colleagues or he doesn't want to disappoint Trump. He wants to do what Trump wants. Now, of course, what Trump really wants is rate cuts and he may in fact end up getting rate cuts. He just can't get them right away. I think they have to maintain some kind of pretense.
Speaker 1: before they cut rates. In fact, there's now a 70% probability that we're going to get a rate hike in the September meeting. Although if the Fed wasn't willing to hike rates now, why would they hike them in September? So my estimate would be that between now and September, the probability of a September rate hike will probably come down.
Even
Speaker 1: though the bond market is screaming and I'll get to that later for a hike between now and September, if the carnage that we saw in the stock market today and this week in tech stocks in particular, if that continues and we start to see weaker economic data.
That
Speaker 1: makes it more difficult for the Fed to hike rates, especially since in September you're getting very close to the midterm elections. So to the extent that there's a lot of damage
from a
Speaker 1: rate hike, you would think they would have wanted to do that damage now in July rather than waiting till September when there may not be enough time between then and the election to recover from that. So to me, I think the
Speaker 1: A rate hike may be even less probable in in September than it was now. Anyway, we're going to take a quick commercial break on the other side of the break. I'm going to get into the Q&A, which is always the most telling part of these press conferences. It's not what the Fed chair reads from prepared remarks.
Speaker 1: But his off the cuff
Speaker 6: responses, although I'm sure a lot of them are rehearsed, they probably have, you know, sample questions. You know, they prepare for these press conferences probably so they're not completely caught off guard. But still, you know, they're not reading from cue cards. They have to answer the questions and then or avoid answering the questions, which is generally what they do, and then maybe getting a follow up. So we've got a quick commercial. We're coming right back. So don't go anywhere.
Speaker 6: Dive
Speaker 7: into the 11th Annual State of Smart Manufacturing Report with Rockwell Automation, hear from manufacturers across the globe, and learn how manufacturing leaders are making decisions that put technology and talent at the core of their competitive strategy. Explore best practices of top performers, benchmark your digital strategy, and learn 2026 investment trends. Talk to any manufacturer in this country right now and
you'll hear the same
Speaker 7: The pressure is coming from every direction, rising energy costs, a tight labor market, supply chains that are still fragile, and cyber threats that get worse every quarter. This isn't one problem you can solve and move on. It's all of them at the same time. Rockwell Automation put together the full picture in their 11th annual State of Smart Manufacturing Report. Over 1,500 decision makers, real data, and real findings. Download it for free at rok.auto slash sos.
Speaker 7: That's R-O-K dot auto slash
Speaker 4: S-O-S-M. All right, so I want to focus on three questions in particular that happened during the press conference, because I think these are the most significant questions, and these are the questions and answers or not answers that I think the markets are focusing on, and now the financial media is...
Speaker 4: Oh, before I do that, there's one point I wanted to make that Warsh said, and this was, he said this in his prepared remarks, and he then, you know, talked about it again in the Q&A. But he said that without the far forward guidance, he likes the fact that.
Speaker 4: long-term interest rates are moving higher. He said that this is good news that both real interest rates and nominal rates are higher. And, you know, I disagree with his assessment about real rates. Nominal rates are definitely higher and they moved a lot higher today.
But I
Speaker 4: think real rates are actually falling because I think the inflation rate is going to be much higher than what the bond markets are assuming. So if you have a benign outlook on inflation, looking at the increase in nominal rates,
you might
Speaker 4: assume that there's also a commensurate increase in real rates. Or maybe you're just looking at the tips or something like that. But I don't think that that's what's going on. I think real rates are actually falling because I think the markets are underestimated.
Speaker 4: how much inflation is actually going to be. But what Warsh said was this is a
Speaker 1: good thing because the markets aren't cheating, because they're not taking their cue from the Fed. And I agree with that. I've never liked the forward guidance where markets are pricing things based on what they think the Fed is going to do, not based on what they believe is economically vulnerable.
Speaker 1: fundamentally justified. They're just focusing on, hey, what's the Fed going to do? So regardless of what we think, we want to price assets based on what we expect the Fed to do. Even if what the Fed's going to do is wrong, it's all about expectations. And he said he doesn't want to do that. And in fact, Warsh specifically said he wants to be able to take cues from the markets.
Speaker 1: And if the markets are pricing thing based off what they expect the Fed to do, then those queues are worthless. He wants to actually see what the markets are doing so he can listen to the markets. So if rates are going up, that means something if they're going up or they're going down. If they're just going up or down because of what they expect the Fed to do, how does the Fed...
Speaker 1: uh learn anything from that if everything that's happening is just based on what it's saying it's
Speaker 6: it's like it's skewing the markets it's interfering with the very results that it wants to use to make policy so uh worse is happy now that the markets
Speaker 1: are kind of doing their own thing although what the markets are doing is telling him that he needs to hike rates and he's not doing it
Speaker 1: And that came up in one of the Q&A. And
in
Speaker 6: fact, I might as well start with that question. That was from Steve Leisman, CNBC's guy. And this was in a follow-up. I forget his initial question because it was the follow-up that I thought was more interesting. And it may have been this very discussion about forward guidance. But he said that, OK, Chair Warsh,
Speaker 6: You're saying that you want to listen to the markets.
And you've
Speaker 6: noted that the markets are moving rates higher. So if you're listening to the markets, what are those markets telling you?
And I was
Speaker 6: hoping to get an answer, and I didn't. He pretty much sidestepped the question, which was a good question, because you're listening to the markets. It's pretty obvious what they're saying. They're saying that rates should be higher, so you should have hiked rates.
Speaker 6: Yet, you
Speaker 1: know, why didn't you do that? And that was really the focus of the other two questions. It's more
of a put up or
Speaker 5: shut up. It's stop talking and start acting because all of this tough rhetoric. And he repeated this in the Q&A. He keeps on talking about
Speaker 5: how committed they are to that 2% target and not even like slightly above like we won't even settle for 2.1 he's not even talking about the right or the left of the decimal point anymore he's like we are committed to getting to 2% and we're going to do whatever it takes despite
Speaker 1: the fact that he's done nothing so one question he got was the reporter said
Speaker 4: well, so far, all you're doing is talking.
Speaker 4: Right. Which is true. He said,
Speaker 5: what are you waiting for? He
didn't answer the
Speaker 5: question. What are you waiting for? He didn't have an
Speaker 1: explanation. Now, he talked about the fact that, hey, we haven't been here that long. You know, it's only been, you know, whatever a month or whatever it is. We're still thinking about what we're going to do. We're still assessing things.
Speaker 5: What's to think about? What's to assess? He's already said that inflation has been way above 2% for more than five years. Why is that? Because rates have been too low for those five years. Because the Fed has created too much money. Because the balance sheet has been too big. You don't need to wait for the recommendations of your task force to tell
Speaker 1: you what's needed. We need higher interest rates and we need a smaller balance sheet. Yet he is delivering neither.
Speaker 1: And in fact, then another reporter asked him to define what he meant by no tolerance for inflation, because he
Speaker 6: kept saying, we have no tolerance for inflation above 2%.
Speaker 5: OK, well, it's well above 2%. What does that mean? Because you say you have no tolerance, but you're not
hiking
Speaker 1: rates. You're not doing anything. Now, one of the things that he kept using as an excuse was that we
Speaker 5: don't have a magic wand.
And
Speaker 5: he must have talked about his magic wand at least two or three times like, well, you know, what are you expecting? We don't have a magic wand. Nobody thinks the Fed has a magic wand, but they do have these tools that they constantly talk about. So why not use your tools? Yes, you can't wave a magic wand, but you can wave your tools or use your tools. You can raise interest rates. It's not a magic wand, but it's something
Speaker 6: that you could do.
Speaker 6: you could shrink the balance sheet you could shrink money supply you could
Speaker 5: do something what the fed is doing is absolutely nothing and then claiming we don't have a magic wand in other words what they're saying or what he's saying is inflation is not
Speaker 1: going to go down because the only way we could reduce inflation is if we could do it by magic.
But unfortunately, we
Speaker 1: don't have a magic wand. So I guess you're SOL, right? You're going to have to, you know, stay with inflation, even though we have no tolerance for it and we are determined to bring it down since we don't have any magic spells to cast. You know, what is the reason, right? When people are not asking themselves, OK, if this guy really is committed, as committed as he says.
Speaker 1: to bringing inflation down to 2%, why did he waste two FOMC meetings and not hike rates? Even when the market was at least opening the door to an expectation
Speaker 5: that rates were going to go up, why not do it? Why not put some words and put some actions behind your words?
There's one
Speaker 5: of two possibilities, right? Either, you know, words is all he's
got.
He
Speaker 5: really doesn't want 2% inflation, or yeah, he'd take it if he can get it, but he doesn't want to do what it takes to get it. He doesn't want to make the trade-offs. He doesn't want to make the choice. So he's thinking, look, if I can get 2% inflation just by talking about it, then fantastic. Because he wants to avoid the other trade-offs. He wants to avoid recession. He wants to avoid stock market crash, real estate crash, financial crisis, all these things that might happen.
Speaker 5: if he really did what it took to bring inflation down. So he wants to cheat. He wants to see if I can get it down just by talking about it. Well, that's obviously not going to work, right? And if he thought
it was
Speaker 5: going to work, he should know by the market reaction, which I'm going to get to, that it is not going to work. And the other possibility is it's all the markets.
He's
Speaker 1: just...
Speaker 1: He knows that the markets are going to go down if he hikes interest rates. So he's not doing it, but he can't say that. So he just has to keep pretending that inflation is going to come down somehow because we got a tough guy in town who's going to talk and talk and talk. And hopefully the markets will, you know, will move based on that, based on just that tough talk, you know, speak loudly, even though you don't have a stick. and he's hoping that
the
Speaker 1: markets don't realize he doesn't have a stick. Well, what's happening now is the markets are reacting to this apparent disparity, the complete difference between the Fed's words and the Fed's actions. And now the Fed is losing credibility.
Speaker 1: Now, Warsh is getting a credibility problem. The markets gave him some credibility.
And remember, I
Speaker 5: kept saying from the beginning, the whole idea that he's going to be an inflation hawk, that he's going to be tough on inflation, that he's going to be another Paul Volcker was all
Speaker 1: BS.
Speaker 1: That there was no chance that that was going to happen because politically it can't happen based on the economic fundamentals. The fundamentals are we have so much debt. This whole economy is such a massive bubble that
if we
Speaker 1: actually tried to do what Paul Volcker did, we would create an economic condition much worse than what they perceive the threat to be from inflation.
Speaker 1: So they're not going
Speaker 4: to do anything. But at this point, I think the Fed is now damned that they do, or we're
Speaker 1: damned if they do, and we're damned if they don't, because even if the Fed doesn't hike rates, the markets are going to crash. If it does hike rates, they're going to crash even more. So it's not that the Fed can look at the market reaction to their lack of a hike and think, well, that means we have to hike.
Speaker 1: No, because when they actually hike, it's going to even be worse for the markets than the sell-off from the non-hike. But I think we're at a point where, regardless, the markets go down because the Fed can't keep sending these missed signals and losing all of its credibility. Because once you realize that the Fed is just BS and worse, it's just talking, it's
Speaker 1: That is a big loss of confidence, especially for the bond market. And if you're losing confidence in the bond market, well, the stock market is going to follow. And what happened to bonds today? Yields rose. The highest I saw the 30-year Treasury was 5.22% on the day. That is the highest it's been in about 20 years, before the 2008 financial crisis. So this is a new high.
Speaker 1: The yield on the 10-year didn't quite make a new high because it got to 4.69, so still didn't see it above 4.7, but we could easily be there by tomorrow. But the decline in bonds is why the stock market sold off. In fact, the market was down before the announcement. In fact, I think maybe on the lows, the Dow was down 700, 800 points.
And
Speaker 1: the NASDAQ was down not quite as much percentage-wise because it got killed the prior couple of days. But when we didn't get a hike, we got a rally in the market. I mean, the Dow didn't go positive. I think it may have been down 300, 400 points at its best. But the NASDAQ reversed and went positive. But when the bond market rolled over and sold off,
Speaker 1: even though the Fed didn't hike. And in fact, not hiking is bad for the bond market because it shows that the Fed doesn't really have zero tolerance for inflation. In fact, I interpret what Walsh did today, leaving rates unchanged, as choosing inflation. That's what he chose. He told everybody inflation was a choice and then that's exactly the choice that he made. Well,
When
Speaker 1: the Fed chooses inflation, people who hold 30-year treasury bonds choose to sell them. And they also choose to buy gold. Gold was down. And I'll get to gold in a minute. Let me just start with the markets. So the bond market sold off. And that's when the stock market rolled over. So the market closed on the lows of the day. The Dow was down 2.2%, which is about $1,100 and change.
Speaker 1: S&P, not quite down as much, 1.5%. The NASDAQ down 1.7%. But the triple Qs, which is the NASDAQ 100, that was down over 2%. And in fact, on the week now...
Speaker 1: That index is down over three percent. As I warned on the podcast I did on on Saturday, I thought we were going to see a bigger pullback in the A.I. related stocks as the air came out of that bubble. And that's exactly what happened. In fact, Meta is getting beat up after hours. It missed on earnings. It's down about 10 percent. Microsoft beat.
Speaker 1: But it's only up maybe a couple of percent. But a lot of the chip stocks have gotten clobbered so far this week, like I warned. I mean,
Speaker 5: one example is Sandisk, which is down 30% so far in the first three
Speaker 1: days of this week. Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, 30% drop. Now, sure, the stock is still way up on the year, but, you know, it's been cut in half and, you know, a big move just in the last few days from that. But gold.
Speaker 1: gold rallied it wasn't a big rally but it didn't sell off that's the key in fact gold was down maybe 20 or 30 bucks before we got the
Speaker 4: decision uh then it rallied just before the decision came about a half hour before got to up 15 bucks or so and it got as high as up 80 dollars um after uh
um
Speaker 4: pal uh warsh was talking during the presser
it got
Speaker 4: up to about 80 bucks but when the bond market rolled over uh that hit that hit the
Speaker 1: stock market and um and and that you know because gold traders look at the yields and they think that rising bond yields are bearish for gold they're wrong they're they're actually bullish for gold and i will get to that we'll take another quick commercial break
Speaker 4: and i'm going to finish up with this a topic on the other side of of that break so So stick around.
Speaker 7: - I've been in the investment
business
Speaker 7: my entire life. One of the most common mistakes that I see is when people treat life insurance like an investment. That's the wrong way to think about it. Life insurance exists to protect the people who depend on you financially if you are not around to do it yourself. That's why term is the right answer for most people. It gives you the biggest death benefit for the smallest premium. And that frees up the rest of your money to make actual investments. Investments that will perform
Speaker 7: A lot better than the cash value sitting inside a whole life policy, which inflation is going to chew through anyway. And the longer you wait, the more it costs. So the rational move is to handle it now while it's cheap and while you don't need it. That's where ethos comes in. The whole process is online. You can get a quote in seconds and apply in just minutes. You can get up to $3 million in coverage and some policies start as low as $30 a month. The ethos makes getting
life insurance
Speaker 7: Fast and easy, 100% online. You can get a quote in seconds, apply in minutes, and get same-day coverage. There's no medical exam. Just answer a few simple health questions. Take 10 minutes to get covered today with life insurance through Ethos. Get your free quote at ethos.com/gold. That's ethos.com/gold. Application times and rates may vary.
Speaker 5: Anyway, I was saying that gold, which had rallied about 80 bucks,
Speaker 5: sold off, but it never went negative. It never went below
Speaker 4: $4,000. And in fact, it closed up about $40 on the day, about $4,070. And silver, which was up about a buck and change at one point, sold off to about unch and then ended up closing up about $0.50 at $57.50. And the reason that gold and silver traders
were
Speaker 4: are worried about rising yields is they think, well, that's bad for gold
Speaker 5: because higher interest rates are bad for gold. Higher bond yields are not necessarily bad for gold. It depends on why those yields are
Speaker 1: rising. And if bond yields are rising because bond investors are losing confidence in the Fed,
Speaker 1: because bond investors are worried that inflation is going to be higher because the Fed is too timid to hike rates or slow money supply growth because it's too worried about adverse effects on the economy,
Speaker 5: that is also bullish for gold because the loss of confidence in the Fed is why you buy gold. If you're worried about higher inflation, that's why you buy gold. it's the same reason you wanted to sell treasuries. In fact, the smart thing
to do
Speaker 5: do as a result of what happened today is to sell treasuries and buy gold. And clearly
Speaker 1: some of that happened today because treasuries went down and gold went up. Gold is the last safe haven standing. And a lot of people I know recently have been questioning whether gold has lost its luster as a
Speaker 1: whether it's no longer a store of value or an inflation hedge, yeah, that's all a bunch of BS. It hasn't lost anything. All people are looking at is, oh, gold got to 5,500 and it went down to 4,000. Who cares that it
Speaker 5: went to 5,500? It's at 4,000. Where was it a couple of years ago? Where was it 10 years ago, 20 years ago, 25 years ago? Gold hasn't lost anything.
Speaker 5: The problem is a lot of people
Speaker 1: never really had confidence in gold because they never really understood it. And they had a lot more confidence in the Fed because they didn't understand the Fed either. They don't understand the Fed and they don't understand gold. But I think more people are going to start to understand that as they start to perceive the dilemma that the Fed is in. They can't hike rates and they can't not hike rates because the markets are going to go down regardless.
of
Speaker 1: of what they do now the dollar was down today as well not a lot but the dollar index slipped back below 101 where i think i'm looking at it 100.84 so again that's also a bad sign a loss of confidence rising interest rates didn't help the dollar now again it's long-term interest rates we didn't get a rise in short-term interest rates because uh the fed didn't have the guts to raise them.
Speaker 1: Also, oil has been on a roller coaster. You know, we got a big drop in oil prices on Monday because Trump de-escalated the rhetoric he escalated. So after talking about bombing this shit out of Iran or whatever he said, I think on Sunday he said, you know what, we're not going to bomb them after all. They're playing nice. And then
I
Speaker 1: don't know, a day later, he came out and said, that's it.
I got
Speaker 1: to bomb the hell out of these guys. And so oil has been on a roller coaster. And in fact, right now, let me check where oil prices are
Speaker 4: trading. Because they were over $90 a barrel when I finished my podcast on Saturday. And they're lower than that now.
Speaker 4: We had a couple of we had Monday and Tuesday oil went down. Today it went up. Now we're back about 84 and a half. But
Speaker 1: we're still trending higher on oil prices, which is also problematic and which is another reason why the Fed should have hiked rates. You know, I'm surprised a little bit that he didn't
Speaker 4: even get more pushback than he did during that press conference for the disparity between the tough talk and
Speaker 1: the failure to act.
Speaker 1: But, you know, CNBC actually was focusing on this. In fact, I think Steve Leesman was reading my
Speaker 4: my ex feeds because he started talking about the markets giving Warsaw a thumbs down. And that was
Speaker 1: like one
of my
Speaker 1: first posts that came out right away. I said that, you know, the market was given a thumbs down to the Fed's rate rate decision. That was the exact word that I used. Now I realize other people might have said thumbs down.
Speaker 1: But I was I was the first one to raise that because I knew exactly what was going on. And I was watching very closely or listening intently, waiting for somebody to ask these questions before they were asked. I was waiting for
Speaker 5: somebody to say, wait a minute. What are you doing here? Why didn't you hike? Give me a valid explanation for why you did not hike. And then when he didn't give one, press him again. Look, are you serious or not?
Speaker 5: Right. It's like, you know, you can't keep talking about how serious you are about solving this big inflation problem. Yet do nothing to solve it, but talk about the fact that you're going to think about solving it. What's there to think about? Just use your tools. You only
have two
Speaker 5: tools, right? That's all you've got in your chest. You know, yeah, there's no magic wand in
Speaker 1: there. We all know that. And nobody expected a magic wand, but we would at least expect you
to
Speaker 1: to use the tools that you acknowledge that you have. Anyway, I expect there to be some more reaction to this overseas back tomorrow as the markets really start to now
Speaker 6: question the Fed and start to ask the questions, why? What are they afraid of? Why aren't they hiking? Because those are the serious questions. Those are the important questions. And once the markets figure out
That
Speaker 1: the Fed can't fight inflation because the adverse consequences are too serious. They can't admit that. So all they
can do
Speaker 1: is talk. But talk doesn't work anymore. There should be a huge rally in gold, huge decline in the dollar. Bonds should continue to fall and this should spill over into an overvalued stock market that needs to increase.
Speaker 1: Come down. Anyway, we got some economic news that came out during the week that I want to mention. Most significant was probably consumer confidence, which unexpectedly took a drop. I think I think one key number in there was at a five year low. So, you know, despite, you know, the claims of how great the economy is coming from not just Donald Trump, but coming from the Fed. Right. We have this really, really strong economy.
Speaker 1: Consumers, you know, confidence part, you know, at a five year low in certain aspects at
Speaker 4: 90.8. Maybe
the Fed
Speaker 4: realizes and that's one of the reasons that the Fed doesn't want to hike is because it realizes that the economy is a lot more fragile than it is publicly pretending by talking about how resilient it is. Yeah, it wouldn't be that resilient if the Fed really started
to fight
Speaker 4: inflation with inflation.
Speaker 4: rate hikes. We also got the
Speaker 1: trade numbers. Again, this is the merchandise trade, the trade deficit for June, $101.5 billion, a little bit less than $105.8 billion in the prior month, but exceeding expectations. But most significantly, it's still north of $100 billion.
Speaker 1: That's what helped. Exports, though, also down 1.8%. You know, I noticed on X, somebody pointed this out and I reposted it. But somebody put up a chart of the last of the 18 months prior to Trump and the 18 months since Trump.
And the
Speaker 1: trade deficit is.
Speaker 1: in goods is actually a little bit higher in the post-18 months than the pre. It was $1,738,784,000 before the tariffs. And now with the tariffs, it's $1,801,377,000.
So
Speaker 5: it's bigger. We have a bigger trade deficit with the tariffs
Speaker 1: than before the tariffs. Now, it's hard to say...
Speaker 1: Where it would be if we had never imposed the tariffs. I mean, maybe the trade deficit would be even bigger than that. I don't know. But one thing for sure, the tariffs didn't turn anything around. They didn't improve our trade deficit.
The trade deficit
Speaker 1: is not lower because we have these tariffs.
It
Speaker 5: still went up. And of course, we had to pay the tariffs on top of that. So we imported a lot more stuff.
And
Speaker 5: we had to pay higher prices because in addition to what the stuff cost us, we had to pay the tariffs. All right. So the tariffs are a complete failure any way that you
Speaker 4: want to look at them.
But what I want
Speaker 4: to talk a little bit more about to end up the podcast is just, you know, I guess I'm going from the sublime to the ridiculous here because I want to talk about Mandami in New York. And he just announced...
Speaker 4: that these new grocery stores
Speaker 1: are
going to
Speaker 1: be opening up in New York. He's going to open up five stores. And he's happy to announce that the prices in these government-owned grocery
Speaker 4: stores are going to be 30% lower.
than
Speaker 4: at, you know, your regular, you know, price gouging, you know, capitalist run stores where the greedy capitalists, you know, just don't care about the consumer and they're just ripping everybody off. Right. And so the government is going to take care of everybody and prices are going to be 30 percent lower. Now, first of all, I mentioned this before in my
Speaker 1: podcast, but grocery stores, supermarkets.
Speaker 1: You've got about the lowest margins of any retailer. They marked stuff up 2%, 1%. Maybe they can get away with 3%. The markups are very low. They make their profit on volume.
Speaker 1: Because, you know, you shop a lot. People go grocery shopping every week, sometimes several times a week. So, you know, people are constantly buying stuff. So the way you make money is you sell a lot of stuff, but you make a little bit of money on everything that you sell. And the reason that you can't
Speaker 5: charge a lot more is because there's so much competition. There's a lot of grocery stores. And by and large, the groceries are the same.
Speaker 5: And so if you try to charge too much, people are going to shop at your competitor.
And so
Speaker 5: because of the competition, prices are low, but you can make money
Speaker 1: because you're selling a lot of stuff. I mean, it's different if you're selling clothes. People don't go buy new clothes every week. They go clothes shopping maybe a few times a year. I mean, not my wife, unfortunately, but a lot of people, they don't constantly shop.
Speaker 1: And so you have a bigger markup because you don't have as much as many sales to to earn your, you know, your money. So when you sell something, you have to have a bigger markup because you don't sell as much stuff. But if people were just, you know, constantly buying new stuff all the time, you know, redoing their wardrobe.
Speaker 1: You know, once a week, yeah, you know, in theory, the markups could be a lot lower and the businesses can make money. But grocery stores are very unique because we constantly eat food and then the food that we buy is gone, right? If I buy clothes...
Speaker 1: I can still wear it, right, unless I, you know, I gain a lot of weight or if you're little kids, they grow up or something. But, you know, you can keep using it. Or if I buy a television set, I don't need to buy a new television set every week. I got television sets that are more than 10 years old. They still work, right? I don't have to keep rebuying them. But with food, you buy it, you eat it, it's gone. You got to go back. You got to buy it again. You got to buy it again, over and over again. So it's a very competitive business.
Speaker 4: How?
Is
Speaker 4: Mandami going to run his stores so that
he could
Speaker 4: charge 30 percent less? Because first of all, there's no way the government run grocery store is going to be as lean and mean and efficient as a for profit grocery store that is run by an entrepreneur who's trying
to make a
Speaker 4: profit. Because if I own a
Speaker 1: grocery store, I need to watch my costs.
Speaker 5: I need to keep my costs low.
Speaker 5: Because whatever I don't spend, that's my money. I earn that. And I have to keep my costs low so I can keep my prices low so I can keep my customers happy so they keep coming back and they don't go to my competitor. But the guys that run the government stores, they don't give a shit about any of this. None of this is their own money. So their overhead, their cost of doing business is going to be higher than any privately owned for-profit grocer.
Speaker 6: yet somehow
Speaker 6: they're going to sell the same groceries for 30 percent less how is that going to happen well it's only going to happen because the taxpayers in New York City are going to be hit with a huge bill to cover those losses to subsidize these money losing grocery stores because the only way they're going to be able to sell groceries for 30 percent below the market is if they lose money
Speaker 6: And they're going to lose even more money than a private company would do if it was selling for 30 percent less because their operation is going to be a lot less efficient and
a lot
Speaker 6: more expensive. So this is going to be a huge loss. But that's just the first part about forget about just how much money New York City is going to lose. And of course, they're going to lose more and more money the longer these stores stay in business. That's the sad part. But.
just
Speaker 1: like anything that a socialist does that they never think anything out they never stop to consider the consequences of their idiotic plans right because they're because these plans are not based on reason or logic they're just meant to sound good right because hey i promised
Speaker 6: cheaper food so here how am i going to deliver we're going to have these government uh grocery stores and
Speaker 6: You know, if the government could deliver food cheaper than the private sector, then we'd all be eating at government, you know, stores, you know, but it doesn't work. I mean, everybody that's tried it, you know, there was a meme that I saw, you know, under capitalism.
Speaker 6: Bread lines up for people because it showed an image of a shopper and there's all kinds of bread. I mean, so many different varieties, you know, brands and kinds of bread and a whole row in a supermarket. It's just bread. Right. And you just, you know, you get picked whatever you want. So
the bread
Speaker 6: is lining up for the for the consumer. But under communism, socialism,
Speaker 6: The people have to line up for bread because you're standing in a long line to get whatever stinking bread they got. You don't have a choice. You can't get rye or pumpernickel or sourdough. You just get whatever they have, and it's probably stale. And you're lucky if you even get that because they probably run out by the time you finish waiting on your long line. But anyway, so here's what's going to happen with these these supermarkets. So first of all, they're going to sell stuff for
Speaker 1: 30 percent less.
Speaker 1: then it's actually worth right now what's going to happen is that people are going to start shopping in these stores and not the for-profit stores because you know they're getting 30% cheaper and
the
Speaker 5: other companies they can't compete with that right how they get they're going to lose money if their margins are two or three percent they can't cut prices 30% that they lose a fortune
Speaker 5: So what happens now is
Speaker 1: people start shopping in these government stores and the more people who shop in these government stores, the more, you know, food and items those
Speaker 6: stores are going to have to sell. Right. So their their volume of their business is going to go up. They're going to sell more stuff at a 30 at a big loss, which means the losses are even bigger. But now what happens is the private sector is.
Speaker 6: Grocery stores now they start going out of business because they're losing business to the government because the government is selling subsidized food below market. So the private companies, they start shutting down. And so now the the real industry in New York City grocery store industry is less competitive.
And
Speaker 6: the stores that are the most likely to shut down are the ones that are in the poorer neighborhoods where the price is even a bigger draw. You know, maybe in the more affluent areas, A, those free grocery stores will be far away from where the customers are. So they may not want to go all the way across town. You know, they may have a premium on proximity, plus also the quality. You know, they may not have the highest quality produce or meats. And so people who are more concerned over quality,
you know,
Speaker 6: may not go there. But people who are very price conscious in the inner cities, in the markets that are closest to these government stores, those are the ones that are going to go out of business first. So now you're creating a situation where the poorest people, the most vulnerable people, you're now destroying the grocery industry in their communities so that now they're going to need these government grocery stores more than ever, because if they ever shut down, there's There's gonna be nothing left. They're gonna be stuck
without any
Speaker 6: private sector alternatives but that's only part of it because here's what's going to happen so the government now is selling groceries for 30 below market what's going to happen people are going to rush into those stores and buy up as much as they can because they can turn around and sell
it i can
Speaker 6: make a business i can go and buy grocery items from the government
and
Speaker 6: 30% below market, and then I can take them to a for-profit grocery store and just, hey, hey, I got all this extra stuff, and I can sell it 10% below market. That's still a good profit for me, and that's still a better deal than a grocer is going to get from a wholesaler, because the government is selling groceries below wholesale, not just below retail, below wholesale.
Speaker 6: So now all these customers can become wholesalers and sell to the other stores. So what's going to happen is the minute these stores open up, these government stores, they're going to run out of merchandise. People are going to rush in and clean out the shelves, which means there's going to be no food there. They're going to be empty.
So people
Speaker 6: aren't going to be able to get any food. That's going to be a big problem. Now, what might the solution be?
Speaker 6: They're going to have to ration. They're going to have to say one loaf of bread per shopper, one carton of milk, like one stick of butter, whatever. They're not going to let people load up on stuff. And so what does that mean? That means there'll be really, really long lines at these government-run grocery stores, just like in the old Soviet Union. So you want to get food 30% below market, be prepared to wait in line a long time. Now, again,
Some
Speaker 6: people, they have maybe they have a job. They can't afford
to wait
Speaker 6: in line all day to buy their groceries. But there are going to be a lot of people who a lot of people who are getting government money there, you know, they're going to have a job anyway. So they'll they'll they'll queue up and they'll stay there. So this whole thing is going to be a disaster. And, you know, as it continues, more people are going to want to buy stuff from these government stores, even though they
have to
Speaker 6: wait in line.
And
Speaker 6: that means even bigger losses for the taxpayer, even bigger losses for the private sector because they lose out on on customers. And so this Mandami is just going to destroy the grocery industry in New York. The only thing that may save it is that if these things are such a big disaster that
That
Speaker 6: there's just no food on the shelves at all because they can't stock it. And the whole thing collapses and nobody even shops there. They may ultimately save themselves because of their own incompetence. But to the extent that they can actually do what they're claiming they're going to
do,
They
Speaker 6: would wreck the industry and they would they would they would basically cause a huge taxpayer loss, which, you know, where are they going to get the money to subsidize all these all these groceries? Look, the bottom line, and this is what the socialists don't get, is the free market does a great job of of distributing goods and services online.
Speaker 6: at the highest quality and at the lowest price. The government can't do it. Government is impossible. I mean, look at the post office, right? Is that an example of efficiency, the way the government runs the mail? No, the government doesn't run anything efficiently because it doesn't have the proper motivation. There is no profit motive. You don't have the right incentives. And so it doesn't work.
And
Speaker 6: why the people of New York don't understand this there, you know, there are so many people who immigrated who came to New York because they fled socialist countries, communist countries. They know firsthand that the government can't can't do this, least of all feeding people. But, you know, all of this, you know, sounds good to a lot of people who, you know, were indoctrinated by government schools.
and
Speaker 6: have no idea how bad socialism is, how bad communism, which is a form of socialism, is that it doesn't work because they didn't learn anything and they don't understand capitalism. And they might understand it better if we actually had it because the problem is capitalism has such a bad rap now because of all the problems that the government has created and has blamed on capitalism. And the other people who want to defend capitalism don't do it the right way.
Speaker 6: That's why it's so important that you share my content with other people because there aren't that many people out there who explain it, who educate people to understand free market capitalism and sound money and how it's supposed to work and who are able to explain the problems that we have in society and
and
Speaker 6: explain how government creates them, how they originate from the government, from regulations, from subsidies, from artificially low interest rates, so that they understand that what they need to be rebelling against is government and government power and government corruption. Capitalism is the solution. That's the only real salvation that works. If you're poor and you don't wanna be poor,
The
Speaker 6: government is not your ticket out of poverty. It's free market capitalism. That's what creates the opportunities. That's what creates the abundance that lifts you out of poverty. The natural state of nature is scarcity. Things are scarce. The reason people are poor is because they can't afford to buy things, because things are too expensive, because there's not enough stuff. Well, if that is the problem, there's not enough stuff, government doesn't make anything. Right?
Speaker 6: If we need more stuff, we need more capitalism. We need more entrepreneurs. We need more risk taking. We need more savings. We need more investment because that's what creates more stuff. So the government has to get out of the way and let capitalism work. What Mandami wants to do is build more government barriers to prosperity to trap people in poverty. So we got to get the message out there. That's why I keep encouraging everybody to not only subscribe to my YouTube channel,
Speaker 6: channel uh for these podcasts but tell your friends to subscribe uh on x follow me there you know my my my subscriber count is really growing that's great better than a hundred thousand a month now you got to follow me on x if you're not following me repost all the posts i did today about the fed uh
Every
Speaker 6: time you see one of those, just repost it. Make sure the people who follow you also see what I'm saying so that they can repost it. We can spread the word. We have a grassroots movement of truth. My perspective would not really get out if it was just dependent on the mainstream media. If they could be the gatekeepers of what the public is able to hear and see,
Speaker 6: The truth would never get out. But we have the Internet. We have social media. So I can bypass those traditional gatekeepers and I can bring the message of truth and capitalism and freedom and sound money directly to to the public. Oh, you know, I totally forgot. I didn't mention anything when I went over the markets, didn't mention anything about
Speaker 1: Bitcoin. And I'll throw that in because.
Speaker 1: Bitcoin has actually been a lot more resilient than I kind of expected. It's barely below $64,000. I mean, it's $63,900 or so. But I wouldn't read anything into that. I don't think that this means that Bitcoin is setting up for a big rally. I just think it's ultimately going to give way. And in fact, a lot of people are being given a lot of opportunity to buy what they think is the bottom.
Speaker 1: And, you know, when you have a lot of opportunities to buy the bottom, it's probably because it's not the bottom. What you're doing is you're buying just before a trap door opens up.
Speaker 4: People are getting suckered into thinking that there's a Bitcoin bottom. And the next thing they know, the rug is going to be pulled right out from under them. Anyway, that's it for today's podcast. Get ready up for the next one that's coming up. And if I
Speaker 1: don't have another one this week, I'm not sure I'm going to be a little bit busy. But if I don't have another one this week, I'll be doing one next week. So bye for now.